In the previous video, you saw me
demonstrate how you can use a simple
calculation to add, subtract, multiply
and divide data within the spreadsheet.
Now, while those tools might be suitable
for a range of tasks that you wish
to do, and there's nothing wrong with
them, there are additional features
and functions within Excel that will
allow you do more complex tasks and
also speed certain processes up.
So if I go back to the Word document
that was downloaded in session one,
and look at what needs to be done.
The very first thing on there
is that the spreadsheet should
allow us to see the following
the total sales for each product.
So if I just click onto the spreadsheet
there, so what that's asking is
that I need to add the cells in row
two for January, February, March,
April, May, June and July together.
Now, as I demonstrated in the previous
video, we could simply click in there.
And type in the equal sign and
then add cell C2 and then add
cell D2, then E2 and F2 and so on.
However, within Excel, you
can use the auto sum function.
Now to access the auto sum there
are two ways you can do that.
You do have a formulas tab along the top,
so that takes you to the formulas toolbar.
And it will give you a range of tools.
So the auto sum tools are there,
recently used financial, and a lot
of these that you may never use, but
there may be some that you find useful.
So have a bit play around with those and
see what, if there's anything in there,
again, you can't damage the data, but in
respect of the tasks that you need to do
for this one, we can access the actual
auto sum directly from the home toolbar.
So if I move along to the right hand
side, I have the little drop down there
with auto sum, and it gives me the most
commonly used formulas or functions.
So I've got sum, average, count
numbers, max and min, but I'm going
to look at here is just the sum.
So if I now click on sum, as
you can see, it's highlighted
all of the cells in row two.
Now a good thing to be mindful of here is
that it will pick up all numerical data,
but we only want the information from
January through to July, but do not want
the price figure included, but because it
is adjacent to that, it will automatically
select it because it is a numerical value.
But I can just reduce the size
of that very similar to reducing
a table or a cell within Word.
I would just click and hold the right
corner, and then drag it along and
then that is only showing that we
have cells C2 to I2 selected, and
you can see that they're in there.
Now, if I just press enter, that will
automatically calculate that there.
I can then go down to the next
cell and do exactly the same
again and click on auto sum.
But again, it will automatically
pick up the price data, but I can
just move that in and press enter.
And that will calculate that.
Don't worry too much about the little
green triangle in the top corner there.
I will explain that in a moment.
An alternative way of doing that
individually is that if I have inserted
the sum formula there, and that is
calculating the data in cell C2 to I2,
I can automate the process for the rest
of the rows by just simply clicking on
the green box in the bottom right-hand
corner, the cursor will change to a black
cross hair and I can just drag that down
and that has entered the same formula.
So it is sum formula, but
it is actually changing.
So it's C5 to I5, C4 to I4.
So it is basically picking
up the data from that row.
So it's just a quick way rather than
having to enter each one manually, you can
do that and it just speeds the process up.
So just coming back to this green
triangle that has appeared in the top
left-hand corner of each of the cells.
This is indicating that there is an error.
And when I click on the cell,
I get a little warning message
that allows me to click on it
and it'll tell me what's wrong.
So it's saying that a formula omits
adjacent cells, which is correct
because we know that the price data is
there, but it shouldn't be included,
but Excel just assumes that all of
the data is numerical so it's telling
us that should that be included?
Because I know it shouldn't be included,
I can just click on ignore error.
And similarly with this one
I could do the same again.
But if I highlighted all of the cells
and then just clicked on that once and
selected ignore error, it will ignore
it for all of the cells in that column.
So now that we have all of the information
in that column, I need to give it a name,
so we know what has actually been shown.
So if I just type Total Sales, and then
click away from that, as you can see that
is clear and I just want to make sure that
the column's wide enough to show that.
So that's telling us that is the
total sales for each product.
If I go back to the Word document, we
also need to look at the next task, which
is the total income for each product.
So to find the total income, what
we need to do is we need to multiply
the price by the total sales.
So we've sold 378 one hour
experiences, 25 pound each.
And we then need to multiply that by that.
So quite simply, this is going back
to the old, simple calculation that
we showed in the previous video.
So if I type in there and go equals,
and it is simply that, and then the
multiplication symbol, which is the star
on the keyboard and by that, press enter.
And that gives us our total income.
So again, I can give the column a heading
just so we know what is being shown and
widen that, just to make sure it's clear.
So as mentioned previously
with the sum formula, I can do
that individually for each row.
But if I wish to just duplicate
that, so it automatically calculates
the total income for the two hour
experience, the half day, the
full,  or weekend experience.
I simply click on the little blue,
sorry, green box in the bottom right
hand corner, and then move that down.
And as you can see, that is calculating
B3 to J3, B4 by J4, B5 by J5.
So it's automated.
It just speeds the process up.
There's nothing wrong with
adding them individually, but
you can speed that process up.
So now that we have the total
sales and total income present.
We need to go back to the Word
document and see what the next task is.
The next task is to show the average sales
of all products for the seven months.
Now, as it wants to see the average
sales for all products over the seven
months, that means it needs a new row.
If it had said that it wanted to
see the total sales for each product
that would have meant a new column.
And we would have used this
column here to show that.
So what we need to do is we're going
to type in thw text Average Sales.
Just below there.
So in column A, we've added
a new row, Average Sales.
And what it's asking is to
show the average sales for each
month for all of the products.
So again, I can click in there
and what I need to do now is if
I go up to the auto sum, and I
can select the average function.
And as you can see, it's automatically
highlighting all of the cells
with numerical data in them.
And if I just press enter, that
will give me the average of all
of the products, which is 15.6.
Again, I can go to the next
column and again, select auto
sum and average, press enter.
And that will give me the average
for February, which was 23.
Again, as I mentioned with regards
to the total sales and the total
income, rather than having to enter
it individually, I can click on the
little green box and then just move that
along till I've got all of them done.
And that will then give me the average
sales for each month for all products.
Excel has a lot more features and
functions that you can use and you
can click on the formula toolbar
to have a look and have a play
around with a variety of these.
We have also included links at the bottom
of the webpage, which will allow you to
practice these skills in greater detail.